4. Who stole my money? I remember when a can of coke was 25 cents.
My parents could buy candy for a penny. Today, you might pay a dollar for a soda, and nothing
costs a penny. So, what happened? Inflation, that's what. Inflation is often called too
many dollars chasing too few goods. It's when prices in a country rise across the board.
If your favorite snack gets a bit more expensive, that's not inflation. But when the price of your
snack, bread, sugar, gasoline, and many other things all rise at the same time, that's inflation.
Inflation means your money buys less than it used to.
Experts have different views on why and how inflation happens. One reason for inflation
is an increase in the supply of money. Generally, when the supply of something goes up, the demand
for it goes down. In other words, its value goes down. So, when there is a lot of money circulating,
each piece of money becomes less valuable. Another cause of inflation is a rise in production
costs. This means it costs more money to make a particular product. The price of a candy bar
may go up if the nuts in it are suddenly more expensive, or if the workers making it are paid
higher wages. Higher taxes can also cause inflation. When items are taxed, people who
produce goods don't want to see their profits go down. Instead, they raise their prices. This is
called transferring the burden to the consumer. It means that producers make the same in profits,
and the people buying the products are the ones who suffer. Inflation is complicated. Track the
prices of some goods you are interested in and see if you can understand why they've changed over time.